[Music]
on the surface
Douglas Murray's recent bestseller the
strange death of Europe was a reaction
to the migrant crisis of 2015 where he
spent months at Europe's borders
interviewing migrants natives and policy
makers but in it he argues that the
migrant crisis and Europeans reaction to
it is another symptom of a broader
spiritual crisis a crisis of meaning and
a sense that the story has run out at a
fundamental level so in a strange death
of Europe you say how long can a society
survive once it unmoored itself from its
founding source and drive yes it is
quite reminiscent like Jordan Peterson
has soared to public consciousness over
the last couple of years with a very
very similar message do you think this
is something that a lot of people are
now waking up to once they're waking up
to I think they're intuiting it I think
have been for a long time and as I said
it takes a little bit of time to be
willing to sort of voice it because it's
as I said not just you may be wrong and
it's embarrassing to be wrong on such a
big thing but it's not so much that as
well what are you going to do about it I
try to just diagnose where I think we
are I'm not particularly prescriptive of
what I think happens now I've got
various instincts about it but I think
that that unmooring and more illness is
I'm not also not the only person to have
pointed it out there are problems about
pointing it out because a lot of people
don't want to accept the premise that
I'm saying there that we that we've
divorced ourselves and the ways in which
we've got where we have because they
think it's a way to open up the door for
religion to come back in or unpleasant
forms of religion to come back in or
very prescriptive forms of religion to
come back in or they think you might be
doing something else
there all sorts of motives you could
ascribe to anyone pointing this out
something you're you're up to secretly
behind the scenes and I think those are
just among some of the reasons why
people are wary about allowing that
conversation to begin because where will
it take us and I'm into that one my own
answer is I don't know I think it's
probably worth it's probably worth
risking it with our eyes as wide open as
possible rather than pretending it away
but yes there are the people who've
you've noticed similar things
doubtless others you could name from
Nietzsche onwards yeah I mean Nietzsche
foresaw a lot of this as did various
others I mean occasionally I get it
happened recently in and in a BBC
interview about Oswald Spengler
the centenary of publication of his
great masterwork and an interviewer said
well you know Spangler said some of what
you're saying a hundred years ago I said
well you know there's there's no
inevitability to the idea that
civilizations become unmoored and then
die or crash within say a four or five
year parliamentary term you know these
things may take a lot of time the second
thing is that as it were the most
positive interpretation of what I am
saying and the most positive
interpretation of the fact that some
other people have said some of it before
the most positive interpretation you
could take from that would be to say
well maybe it's the case that we're
often having bad diagnoses like this as
it were almost terminal diagnosis and
yet we survived and therefore maybe and
this is this is it were the most
positive point that you could make
against what I'm saying maybe in that
case premature or possibly premature
diagnosis of our own mortality as
civilizations maybe something that keeps
us healthy could be it's not such a bad
thing to bear in mind but I mean that's
that's the best-case scenario of course
in the debates with Sam Harris and
Jordan Peterson you said we may be in
the midst of discovering that the only
thing worse than religion is its absence
yes
is this a little bit I'm reminded of GK
Chesterton's idea that if a man stops
believing in God he starts believing in
anything is what you're saying there
that we we have the capacity for very
fundamentalist ways of looking at the
world and we will attach them to
anything part of what we're going
through at the moment is the discovery
that we don't have very much to hold on
to and by that I mean among other things
that we can no longer even agree on
facts seems this is worse in some
countries and others I'd have thought at
this stage in its development America
has this worst but as the Irish
journalist Kevin Myers said a few years
ago something I'm fond of quoting he
said in his memoir watching the door he
described a moment where he said the
truth had become whatever you were
having yourself now we are we are
reaching a similar stage it seems to me
certainly Morocco is already at that
stage you can you can see it everyone
nobody can agree on what's true nobody
can even agree on what's happened not
just historically where everyone has now
got their own view of history regarding
their own political side but also what
happened today even today's facts are
disputed and not as if they ever reach a
conclusion now they just they just go
off in different directions and and I
think that that is a version of what I'm
that's a part of what I'm trying to say
when I say that that we may be
discovering that the only thing worse
than religion is its absence is that the
people seem to be finding it extremely
hard and I don't absolve myself from
by the way I'm not saying that I sit in
some unique position where I don't
suffer from this I think we all do to
some extent but I think people are
finding it very hard to know what it is
you do hold on to what you can hold on
to what art but is another way fixed
certainties now religion in among many
other things provides people erroneously
we may think but with fixed certainties
for instance the biggest of which is
some kind of cosmic idea of justice and
a watered down version of which we
imbibe in our societies today what is it
that the rug on the floor of the Oval
Office said but in the arc of human
history is long but it tends towards
justice there's not a lot of evidence
for that rug being true but it's a
wonderful idea and probably hard to live
entirely without religion provides among
other things that idea it gives you the
idea that if not now then in a future
world you will see justice and it's a
wonderful idea and there are many
smaller concepts which religion probably
alone can provide which without it
people struggle one obvious example
being one that obsesses me is how do you
how do you actually believe not just get
told to follow through on or at least
but how do you actually believe in the
in the concept of the sanctity of human
life I'm not trying to get on on to
abortion or anything on this but how do
you believe in the sanctity of human
life as we live it in the absence of
religion well we have a version of it in
human rights which is a sort of a
non-religious attempt to enshrine a
religious idea but it's filled with
trouble and there's I say there in that
concept is a very very deep and
important thing to hold on to God knows
we need to hold on
to it but you can see how even that
slips slips that are that the margins it
slips at the edges and and in the
absence of that if we are as I think we
obviously are meaning seeking beings
whether or not there is meaning and I
think the second bit of heart for the
time being but if we are indeed meaning
seeking beings then we will keep coming
up with religions and I think that's
what's happening at the moment broadly
speaking in the cultures at the how our
news is filled with religious urges and
religious stories and am a newly
emerging priesthood with a newly
emerging set of Commandments and a newly
emerging set of blasphemies and heresies
and punishments and shaming Xand
floggings all on social media some on
social media and some in the real world
I mean I'm always struck by the way in
which by the number of people who say to
me well things that you are able to say
and think about and write about and so
on if I said it in my job I'd probably
lose it now and that's that's one of
them and of course we can all name
people who that has happened to it
that's one of the things isn't it means
that almost anything anything can be
pushed it's an obvious perhaps too much
of a cliche to say but it's in very
short in a very short period of time
it's become really quite hard to tell
what's at are and what's real in our
world they keep on getting clogged up or
mixed up together you notice they seem
to dance together and sometimes it's
revealed that the satire is real and
sometimes emerges of the real is satire
and i think this leads to an enormous
discombobulation and yes there is a very
clear as I see it religious impulse
throbbing
through our society today creating a new
religion by the way I just preferred the
old ones and believe in them but I
preferred the old ones or ill and all
not least because I think you knew where
you stood and we just no damn idea where
you stand with this one I mean who knew
that if you're a woman who said that you
thought that being a woman involved
having a vagina that you'd be some kind
of absolutely despicable heretic in 2018
you knew that if you a woman on the
labour left who campaigned for all-women
shortlists which is not particularly
south something I'm in favor of but
who'd of who'd have predicted that if
you're a woman in in favor of all-women
shortlists and you'd be campaigning for
ages for them that in 2018 if you said
look like that that girl with a penis
can't be on the old woman's shortlist
you'd become some disgusting
unmentionable bigger we wouldn't have
seen that coming even two years ago
probably and is that the main religion
that you're that you're seeing it's
wondering it's one of them but it could
be absolute I mean I sort of point to X
it could be anything I mean Saul Bellow
has said in the early 80s you said that
he said already that America was getting
to the position that morality in America
he said I think you can say this wider
the morality now but he said morality in
America had become a ghost town
the problem with ghost towns is that
almost anybody can come in and declare
themselves sheriff who would you rely
upon now to tell you something was true
or not
it's who would you nominate who if you
nominated them would you feel you could
get the agreement of everyone else in
society to nominate it's pretty it's
getting hard
I think these lots of these points sort
of the difficulty in making sense of the
world who do you trust this whole idea
of heresy
links into the concept of the
intellectual dark web in in some sense
if there is something that links many of
the figures together it's that they have
been heretics to their own tribe you
sort of take Sam Harris and the Ben
Affleck or Brett Weinstein being kind of
run out of evergreen what what do you
make of the IDW I think it's it's a very
smart concept to try to corral a very
difficult group of very disparate people
into one orbit I think Jordan P doesn't
call it a herd of cats when I asked him
about it
yes that's that that's possible I think
that there is some resistance to it
within its own proclaimed membership
relatively few people say I'm you know
I'm I DW or something I mean I don't I
don't
specially think of myself in this regard
because I suppose I never take you think
of clubs of which I'm a member all
parties or movements or anything like
that so maybe I would maybe would be a
movement for people who don't join
movements I don't know club for people
who don't like clubs I've I think so I
think it's it's it's got all sorts of
inbuilt awkwardness but I think it's
also on Eric Weinstein when he came up
with it I think it's definitely on to
something it's something like I've tried
to think about it and I think it's
something like people who have trodden
on one of the IEDs of our time and have
survived now there's a very interesting
question as to why some people set off
one of the societal bombs waiting to
catch people out and everything is over
and done with and others seem to be able
to
it and survived but it's got something
to do with being outside of the normal
gate keeping organizations I think
something like that but the real
underlying thing is this I think which
is that it is preposterous that almost
everything that is true is so hard to
say in public and so controversial the
same public and so disputed and so so
how old against I think everybody who's
being described as a member that I had
the IDW probably has among other things
one thing in common which is they all
they used to being held at for saying
things that are self-evident how all
that in public only to then discover
that the public come up to them in
private and say thank you so much for
saying what we think and of course
that's one of the beauties of it that's
one of the beauties of technology at the
moment is that the gatekeepers I'm
having just said that all the problems
of not being able to appoint gatekeepers
anymore but that there's a whole set of
things where the gatekeepers have sort
of let everybody down I think and I
suppose I'm not saying that I or anyone
else can do it either individually or
collectively but it seems to devolve
onto individuals to say and think about
things that are of wider relevance and
all of the gatekeepers think our
questions we should be engaging in I was
very struck somebody came up to me after
the event in London with Sam and Jordan
and said they have they had a copy of
that day's New York Times and I paid one
two and three I think
something to do with trans and this
person said this his wife he Polly yeah
that's it not yeah because of the New
York time running so much about trans
and we didn't address any anything to do
with that tonight but I got what he
meant it was like we're being given
really weird quite fringe staff all the
time as our diet and we're starting to
rebel and in the the Sam Harris from
Jordan Peterson debate would you say
that you were
I mean you've talked about your concerns
of what happens if we lose religion or
religious faith would you say you're
closer to Jordan or to Sam on that point
it sounds like you're closer to Jordan
I'm slightly equi distant i am i don't
have sam's belief I don't have any put
another way I don't have Sam's faith in
the idea that if we just brush away the
remaining bracken from religion left by
religion that we get to this reasonable
rational world and I wish him obviously
well not just as a friend but I wish him
well and pursuing that idea and winning
but there's an awful lot of historical
examples of people trying something
relatively similar and then discovering
that they're right back at square one
when Danton Rose Vieira standing outside
not radar min Paris after Revolution and
they work out they can make this a
Cathedral of Reason you know I mean
there's a lot of it there's a lot
there's a lot about the pursuit of
reason and rationalism that suggests
that we're not great at it actually
individually or collectively or to put
it another way that we can keep on doing
just terrible things and sometimes newly
terrible things so that's an obvious
prejudice as it were of my own and yet I
think that what Jordan is saying or
doing with religion which i think is
extraordinary and admirable and tough
for anything else right it's quite
amazingly multi-disciplinary
I mean that's one of the amazing things
about what he's been able to do and what
was a pleasure about listening to him
I'm watching him in those debates he was
one evening I think in Dublin he just
tried to only approach things from using
biology you know it's amazing an amazing
sight and achievement but I I'm not sure
where that's going I'm and I'm
sympathetic with Sam when he tries to
pin Jordan down and Jordan gets out of
the pinning down I'm sympathetic to both
of them in that my own my own position
I'll I suppose is it I'm pretty willing
to answer the questions that Sam would
pose on I don't know Jordan for instance
would find it doesn't want to won't well
no let me be if you asked Jordan do you
believe in the physical resurrection he
would not say yes or no he would
do a brilliant extrapolation of a lot of
thoughts and maybe that is right maybe
you shouldn't be able to just yes or no
I think in my own case I can say I'm
pretty confident it didn't happen but
I'm confident to say that it didn't
pretty much confidence it didn't happen
and also say that doesn't mean that I'm
going to follow sam harris into a world
of pure reason and rationalism because i
don't think it's much more achievable i
think i've myself arrived at the
position of believing you have to be
careful on warring on things which have
given you something of worth and I
respect Jordans enormous ability and
passion in trying to re-inject that
particular part of worth back into the
substructure of the society which i
think is one of the things he's managing
to do do you have any sense I mean
you're sort of saying that we can't do
without religion in some sense or we cut
and we can't sort of reinvent our own
values we've we've we've shown many
times that we can't reinvent our own
values do you have any sort of sense of
how we kind of resolve that is it a new
religion is a new kind of historically
it's the invention of a new religion or
war it's a pretty good time if you
wanted to start a religion now would be
a great time thought must have crossed
your mind if you were to claim since no
one's done it very plausibly for a while
but if you were to claim that that you
had yourself dipped the bucket right
down into the well and brought up
bucket full of the real thing you could
do quite well these days I think it's
one of the I sensed him the debates with
Sam and Jordan I sensed that it was one
of the things that was constantly
hovering I don't know if you agree we're
constantly hovering over the events
Jordan in London gave a very moving and
spellbinding description of a
conversation sort of prophet nature of
the two of them you mean yes
specifically focusing on Jordan I think
I think that Sam's followers and
admirers I think on and expecting any
kind of breakout beyond what he's said I
don't I mean there's lots more for Sam
to cover and talk about but I don't
think there's anything they don't think
they've I don't think I think there's
anything that hasn't yet happened in a
way and I thought that when Jordan
started describing in London a
conversation with a figure of what he
saw as God the Father you could sense in
the audience a feeling of is something
going to happen now it was a
spellbinding moment but there's
something I it just goes back to the
point I was trying to make was is that a
plausible attempt to reassert a set of
very basic truths and claims that
religions have always made with very
ripe firt at the moment and my own view
is that were quite lucky that some total
charlatan and shit hasn't come along
with enormous power already to do that
maybe it's less possible in the modern
Information Age that would have been
even in the time of the founder of
Mormonism but let alone in what used to
be called the age of the prophets but
it's always there isn't it and and and
if you have things like massive societal
upheaval or war or catastrophic events
we're all totally available it's
terrifying
returning to the IDW it's it's been
framed as an alternative sense making
network and in that sense that that's
where you I hear that that's said in the
accent to the Weinstein brothers yeah
you're it's very a lot of the people
within it Joe Rogan Dave Rubin have have
created Sam Harris as well have created
new media platforms distinct from the
mainstream media as an alternative to
the mainstream media you're grouped
within this organization or this loose
grouping but you're the associate editor
of The Spectator magazine what's it say
about the different media landscapes
well I think a lot of us have a foot in
on the foot out I mean I don't think any
of us so is it were complete outsiders
and I don't think anyone has ever
pretended they were Jordan has spent his
life with positions at the top
universities in the world and Eric is a
head of teal capital and I've not been
exactly silenced during my career well
it's not successfully and have a large
number of publications and medium
mediums o open to me and I'm very
grateful lucky but so I think that it
doesn't it's wrong to think of it as
being an insider outsider thing or a or
an establishment anti-establishment
thing or something like that
I'm not certain that there's a massive
difference between America and Europe or
American the UK in in terms of this I
know that in in Europe and the UK the
culture wars are fought slightly
differently than they are in America
because the the area of contestation is
different and the width of the
conversation is different and now after
all there's a lot of stuff that we've
sort of pretty much for good and for ill
agreed upon in Europe that is not agreed
upon in America so I'm not certain there
is any kind of transatlantic divide what
are you thinking of if what we're seeing
in the u.s. at the moment is that the
center cannot hold
there is a kind of increasing
polarization and a lack of agreement as
to what even the facts consist of in
some sense in the UK we have a bit we
have the BBC we have some sense of a
Civic space that is not completely
polarized
although isn't it the case everyone says
so at the moment that the BBC is coming
in for endless attack and there's
actually feeling the attack and I think
it probably is
from the left and from the right at the
moment possess that wouldn't get a bore
on British politics the moment I mean
the anti brexit people think the BBC's
probe wrecks at the probe X that people
think the BBC is anti bricks that the
core bonuses think that the BBC is
institutionally anti Corbin and
conservatives seem to think that BBC is
giving Corbin a great big leg over the
wall of number 10 Downing Street so so
it's uniting people well there's a
fallacy there which which a lot of
people at the BBC and others for for
which is must be doing something right
since I'm getting criticized from both
sides and it's the fallacy often because
you can be criticized by absolutely
everyone that's because you're totally
wrong
there's a there's a weird by the way can
I point this out there's a weird thing
of what I think of as being equi
distance isn't it's an ugly ism but
where people think
if they oppose something there they
don't quite know how they hold the
ground they feel they're in so what they
do is they get something there to the
other side and there they say well you
see I'm standing between these two
things I'm I'm very very worried about
this tactic because I've seen it used
among other things against many of my
friends and against me for many years I
remember more than a decade ago somebody
writing from as it happens the Muslim
Brotherhood in The Guardian claiming
that ayaan Hirsi Ali Martin Amos and me
were merely the flip side of the coin of
Osama bin Laden and you'll notice what
he did there and noticed that neither I
nor Aiyar nor Martin have flown planes
into buildings were told anyone else to
do so mob in court anyway Lobby in court
no you know it's it's so once you've
seen it done to somebody or had it done
to you that kind of other side of the
coin ISM becomes a very cheap trick I
pretty much resist it myself
you see it everywhere okay we've found
somebody who we can accuse of that from
the left let's find somebody from the
right we can accuse it also says it's a
sort of but it's it's the sort of game
that people start to play when they feel
there's nowhere else to hold on to on
the waterslide
you know let me get something for both
sides to hold myself something like
steady so I'm not entirely persuaded
that the media landscape is that defined
it or the distinct difference but it it
probably is the case in Britain there's
a there's there's less of the complete
talking past each other than has emerged
now in the u.s. it's possible there is
some agreement still about reality in
the UK do you have any sense
are you very pessimistic about this kind
of increasing polarization or do you
have any sense of how we pull out of
this spiral I'm um
well I'm in this cause for optimism and
pessimism isn't there as a restraint in
everything um I'm pessimistic in the
fact that I think that people are
becoming so incredibly embedded and
irrational in their embeddedness and I
mean I just able to say it seems to me
absolutely thing now I'm very I'm very
pessimistic about that I think I'm
pessimistic about what I describe as a
tendency to talk about each other and
not to each other I spent part of my
summer touring Australia and New Zealand
with dr. Cornel West the point of the
engagements for me at any rate being
that and I think for Cornell as well
being to demonstrate that people from
totally different political traditions
could sit on stage for hours at a time
night after night talking about
important things not not dodging things
not ducking but being able to have a
rich and meaningful dialogue and sorting
some things out you know which I think
we did actually between ourselves if not
for anyone else and I'm very struck by
how few people do that and as obvious
there's lots of reasons for why that's
happened we all know and I'm afraid that
the mainstream media has been a massive
component of that strange degrading
tendency but the thing that you can be
optimistic about in it is that it's
obvious that new things are coming
through I mean and this is this is
always the way isn't it I mean you can
you can berate and be well as I do the
YouTube ization of discussion that means
that the BBC or ITV or let alone some of
the American networks will get on
one absolutely shouty crazy nutter from
one direction then one apps he shouted
crazy nutter from another and call that
a discussion and that I believe embeds
itself with a new generation of people
who think that is discussion you can be
wailing boom own that but look what
we're doing now is the demonstration of
the opposite which as it turns out yes
that can happen and it also turns out
that there's a reaction to that which
means that there's an audience for long
form often multi-hour discussions I mean
this so there's always there's always
both reason for optimism and pessimism
in this I the thing I'm most nervous
about is is that we need we do need to
find some way to agree on certain tent
pegs certain lines it's it's just it's
just very difficult as you're going
through it
vocals Murray thank you very much
[Music]
you